William Higginbotham Papers 2011.0083
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
William Higginbotham Papers
undated, 1895, 1902, 1931-1972
2011.0083
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
4.5 Linear feet Ten boxes of photographic prints and negatives.
William Higginbotham has photographed railroad locomotives and scenes since the 1930s. The papers consist of images of railroad locomotives and cars, stations and structures and other scenes, of street railway cars New England and of trains and scenes of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and the New York Central Railroad.
Higginbotham, William
Related material:
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Scope and Content:
The collection contains approximately 850 photographs (color and black and white) and negatives of images of railroad locomotives and cars, stations and structures and other scenes in New England and New York State, almost all of them taken by William Higginbotham from 1938 to 1970. A majority of the images are of trains of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and the New York Central Railroad. Most of the images taken by Mr. Higginbotham have an index card of descriptive information usually providing location, date, railroad line and type of train, or type of structure. The collection consists of a small number of photographs gathered by Mr. Higginbotham, mostly of scenes of New England street railways.
Access conditions:
The collection is open and available for research.
Biography:
William Higginbotham was born on October 7, 1921, in Vermont, to parents who worked as dairy farmers. He took up photography in high school and began to photograph trains and railroad scenes. He moved to Massachusetts with his family while still in high school and then to Texas to work as a telegraph operator. He lived in New York where he worked as a teletype operator for UPI and was a member of the Electric Railway Association, New York Division, and the Branford Electric Railway Association. Mr. Higginbotham would vacation around the United States taking photographs of trains. He came to Connecticut around 1999 and lived in Vernon. As of 2011 he lives in Westerly, Rhode Island.
Arrangement:
Series I: Photographic Prints and Negatives (undated, 1895-1972)
Acquisition information:
The collection was donated in August and December 2011 by Mark C. Higinbotham, a cousin of William Higginbotham.
Custodial history:
The collection was held, processed and described by Robert LaMay of Amston, Connecticut, immediately prior to its donation. Mr. LaMay acquired them from Mark C. Higinbotham in Spring 2011.
Higinbotham, Mark C.; Negatives (photographic).; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Photographs.
- Series I: Photographic Prints and Negatives, undated, 1895-1972
  - Subseries A: New England railroads excepting the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, undated, 1895-1972
    - Branford Electric Railway Association (undated, 1948-1972); Central Vermont Railway (1938-1965); Compounce & Gillette Railroad (June 5, 1960); Connecticut Company motor cars (1941-1953); Mount Washington Cog Railway (1956 August 9), undated, 1938-1972 (Box 1)
    - Narragansett Pier Railroad (1941, 1951); Edaville Railroad (1948 September 18); Bay State Street Railway (undated); Biddeford & Saco Railroad (undated, 1940); Greenfield & Montague Transportation Area (undated); Greenfield & Turners Falls Street Railway (1895); Maine Central Railroad (undated, 1934-1938); Montpelier & Wells River Railroad (undated, 1931-1937); Rutland Railroad (undated); Springfield Street Railway (undated, 1939); Public Service Company of New Hampshire (1938-1939); Union Street Railway (1941); United States Armory (undated); United States Maritime Commission (undated); Worcester & Webster Street Railway (1902); Rock of Ages Corporation (1938); United Electric Railway (undated, 1940); Worcester Street Railway (1939-1942); Granite Railway (1941); Massachusetts Northeastern Street Railway (1942); St. Johnsbury & Lake Champlain Railroad (1938-1955); Bridgton & Harrison Railway (1937-1938); Wood River Branch Railroad (1941 July 8), undated, 1895-1955 (Box 2)
    - Large prints, or images from publications, of engines and streetcars, mostly of street railways (note that none were taken by William Higginbotham; photographers generally unknown), undated (Box 10)
  - Subseries B: New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, undated, 1935-1961
    - Locomotives and cars, undated, 1937-1961 (Box 3)
    - Stations and structures, 1953-1961 (Box 4)
    - Photographic prints (1957-1961) and pieces of film, of New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad trains, most in the New York locations of Woodlawn, Larchmont, New Rochelle, Port Chester, Mott Haven; small photographic prints or negatives of railroad cars and engines (some for street railways) in Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, and Vermont (1935-1941)., undated, 1935-1961 (Box 7, Box 10)
  - Subseries C: New York Central Railroad, undated, 1937-1961
    - Prints of engines, most taken in upstate New York and northern New Jersey, undated, 1937-1959 (Box 8)
    - Prints and negatives of engines, most taken in upstate New York (River Division) and northern New Jersey with a few taken in Chicago, Illinois, and Petersburg, Indiana, 1941-1961 (Box 9)
  - Negatives of images held in boxes 1-4 (Note that not all prints had accompanying negatives), undated, 1930-1961 (Box 5-6)